Register of the Pavel Timofeevich Filip'ev Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Pavel Timofeevich Filip'ev papers
1925-1981
2000C117
Hoover Institution Archives
(2.4 linear feet) 16 microfilm reels
Writings, notes, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to the authenticity of the Vlesova Kniga, the early history of Russia and the Slavs, and Russian émigré affairs.
Filip'ev, Pavel Timofeevich, 1896-1981
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
P. T. Filip'ev was born in Ekaterinodar on 14 December 1896 (O.S.). He graduated from the Ekaterinodar School of Arts in 1915, was drafted into military service the same year, and commissioned as an officer following training at the Tiflis Military School in May 1916. He saw action in the Caucasus during the First World War, and served in Siberia and South Russia during the Civil War, eventually being evacuated with General Baron P. N. Vrangel's army. From 1920 to 1925, he worked as a painter and draftsman in Yugoslavia.
In 1925, Filip'ev moved to Prague, Czechoslovakia, to continue his studies at the Russian Higher School of Transportation (Russkoe vysshee uchilishche tekhnikov putei soobshcheniia), graduating in 1928 as a transportation technician. This gave him the opportunity to find employment as a surveyor, project manager and auditor in the highway section of the Czechoslovak State Construction Department, where he worked until 1941. With the advent of the Second World War, Filip'ev was forced to change employment several times, working as an artisan and a teacher at a high school in Klatovy, Czechoslovakia, before illegally crossing the border into Allied-occupied Germany in January 1947. After working there at a variety of jobs, including policeman, tanner and toymaker, he left for the United States in 1951.
In America, he became intensely interested in the so-called "Vles-Kniga," devoting most of the remainder of his life to examining and deciphering it and attempting to prove its veracity, although it has long been dismissed as a forgery by all competent scholars. Filip'ev died in San Francisco in September 1981.
Chronology
1896 December 27 (N.S.) Born, Ekaterinodar, Russia
1916 Graduated, Tiflis Military College
1920 December Arrived in Yugoslavia, employed as a draftsman, and artist
1925 May Arrived in Czechoslovakia as an engineering student
1928-1941 Served as a highway engineer in the service of the Czechoslovakian government
1947-1950 Employed as a policeman, tanner, draftsman, sculptor and in various other capacities in Munich, Germany
1951 Emigrated to the United States
1981 September Died, San Francisco, California
Scope and Content Note
The centerpiece of this collection is Filip'ev's research material: clippings, correspondence, notes, printed matter, and writings associated with his interest in early Russian history, particularly the so-called "Vles Kniga" or "Doshchechki Izenbeka," a forged series of writings alleged by believers to have been produced on the territory of Russia prior to the introduction of the Cyrillic alphabet. Filip'ev expended an enormous amount of time and energy deciphering these writings and attempting to prove their veracity, as well as arguing that they represented an entirely new vision of early Russian and Slavic history. His correspondence and notes on this and related topics shed light on the story of the emergence of this forgery and its effect on the émigré community as well as on believers in the Soviet Union.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Forgery of manuscripts.; Russia.; Russians--United States.; Slavs--History.; Ukraine--History--To 862.; Ukraine.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1925-1972 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Addresses and telephone numbers, curriculum vitae, employment, identity, immigration and school records, papers relating to Filip'ev's illegal crossing of the German border in 1947, ration cards and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1951-1981 (Box 1-2)
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1962-1977 and undated (Box 2-4)
  Drafts of articles, books, letters to the editor, and short stories arranged alphabetically by title
- Subject File, 1954-1981 (Box 4)
  Bulletins, clippings, correspondence, leaflets, and writings, arranged alphabetically by heading
- Vles Kniga File, 1957-1970s (Box 5-15)
  Includes notes, printed matter (clippings, offprints, photocopies, and citations from published works), and writings related to Filip'ev's interest in the Vles kniga and the origins of the Slavs, with supplementary materials relating to Etruscans, the Zagreb mummy, ancient India, Scythians, early Russian history, and related topics
- Photographs, 1980 and undated (Box 15)
  Two prints depicting Filip'ev (one from 1980), two depicting Dominican College, San Rafael, California, and six negatives depicting the Vles kniga
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1925-1972 (Box 1)
  - Addresses and telephone numbers (Folder 1: 1)
  - Curriculum vitae (Folder 1: 2)
  - Employment records. (Folder 1: 3)
    General note
    See also identity papers
    Includes certificates, membership cards, passes, permits, recommendations and unemployment records.
  - Identity papers. (Folder 1: 4)
    See also employment records
    Includes authorizations, residence and travel permits, substitute birth certificates, and similar matter.
  - Immigration papers (Folder 1: 5)
  - Medical records. (Folder 1: 6)
    Includes correspondence with social services
  - Papers relating to his illegal crossing of the German border in, 1947 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Ration cards (Folder 1: 8)
  - School records (Folder 1: 9)
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 10)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1951-1981
  - General
    - General, 1952-1981 and undated (Folder 1: 11)
    - Unsent letters, n.d. (Folder 1: 12)
  - Unidentified, 1952-1966 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Amvrosii, Archimandrite, 1977 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Arheološki muzej, Zagreb, Yugoslavia, 1962-1968 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Bogunskii, Sviatoslav Nikolaevich and Nikolai Sviatoslavovich, 1975-1978 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Bokach, Fedor, Rev., 1968 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Clodt, Boris, 1967 (Folder 1: 18)
  - De Clapiers Collongues, Olga, 1967-1968 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Djordjevic, Bogdan, 1951 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Dolgopolov, Aleksandr, 1969 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Dunaev, V., 1960 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Filippov, Boris Andreevich, 1980 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Kal'skii, Iurii Grigor'evich, 1968-1969 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Kazakov, Nikolai Vasil'evich, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Kol'chitskii, Boris, 1973 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Kolycheva, Elena, 1974-1979 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Krylatov, Vladimir Stepanovich, 1968-1972 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Kur (Kurenkov), Aleksandr Aleksandrovich, 1960-1967 and undated (Folder 2: 5)
  - Liashevskii, Stefan, 1966 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Lysenko, Ivan Erastovich, 1964-1966 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Pallotino, Massimo, 1965-1966 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Perkhorovich, Iurii, 1967 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Platunov, Konstantin, 1967 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Pushkarev, Sergei, 1964 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Riasanovsky, Nicholas V., 1964 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Shchavinskii, V., 1966 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Struve, Gleb P., 1964 and undated (Folder 2: 14)
  - Stumpff, Georg, 1951-1952 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Szeftel, Marc, 1968-1969 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Tolstoy Foundation, 1963-1964 and undated (Folder 2: 17)
  - Turianitsa, Mikhail Il'ich, 1965-1977 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Unbegaun, Boris Genrikhovich, 1968-1969 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Vaughan, Agnes Carr, 1968 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Vernadsky, George, 1969-1970 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Zhigulev, N., 1966 (Folder 2: 22)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1962-1977 and undated
  For Filip'ev's participation in polemics relating to the Vles Kniga and early Russian history (letters to the editor and newspaper articles), see VLES KNIGA FILE
  - General, 1962-1977 and undated (Folder 2: 23)
    Letters to the editor and short stories
  - "Slovo o Polku Igoreve," new translation and commentary
    - Background materials (Folder 2: 24)
    - Correspondence, 1966 (Folder 2: 25)
      Includes letters to and from prospective publishers with attachments relating to costs, fonts, ink types, etc.
    - Holograph. (Folder 2: 26)
      Includes notes, artwork, sketches, tables of contents and format sheets
    - Holograph (Box-folder 3: 1-4)
    - Typescript. (Folder 3: 5-6)
      Includes holograph notes and inserts
  - Untitled work(s) of a philosophical/psychological nature (Box 4)
    - Notes (Folder 4: 1-2)
    - Holograph (Folder 4: 3)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1954-1981
  - Beliaevskii, V. A. Clippings related to Beliaevskii's books on the Russian Civil War and attacks on General A. I. Denikin (Folder 4: 4)
  - Hymns, Russian. (Folder 4: 5)
    Clippings, correspondence and writings relating to polemics (involving Filip'ev) about the Russian national anthem and various substitutes for it
  - Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, California (Folder 4: 6)
  - Odessa (Folder 4: 7)
  - Religion (Folder 4: 8)
  - Soviet Union--Social conditions (Folder 4: 9)
  - Von der Osten, Dirk (Folder 4: 10)
  - Miscellany (Folder 4: 11)
- VLES KNIGA FILE, 1957-1970s (Box 5-15)
  Includes notes and background materials (clippings, offprints, photocopies, and citations from published works), and writings related to Filip'ev's interest in the Vles kniga and the origins of the Slavs, with supplementary materials relating to Etruscans, the Zagreb mummy, ancient India, Scythians, and related (to Filip'ev's mind) topics
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1980 and undated (Box 15)
  See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Identity papers for photographs attached to passport and other documents. Two prints depicting Filip'ev (one from 1980), two depicting Dominican College, San Rafael, California, and six negatives depicting the Vles kniga